const e="englishlit",t=200,o=62,a=[{id:100,question:"The thematic pre-occupation of de Graft’s  Sons and Daughters can be summarized as ",option:{a:"the import of Western education ",b:"the roles of women in modern economy ",c:"how to become a lawyer ",d:"dimly life in the face of social changes."},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:101,question:"Lawyer Bonu in de Grafts Sons and Daughters can be described as a: ",option:{a:"caring father ",b:"faithful husband ",c:"deceitful friend ",d:"shrewd politician."},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:102,question:"De graft’s Sons and Daughters is structured into: ",option:{a:"three acts ",b:"four scenes ",c:"two acts ",d:"five Episodes."},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:103,question:"The central  conflict in de Graft’s Sons and Daughter is primarily: ",option:{a:"political ",b:"generational ",c:"racial",d:"communal"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:104,question:"He already had five wives and was soon going to break the legs of the antelope for the sixth time’. The expression ‘break the legs of the antelope’ means to: ",option:{a:"be ON honeymoon ",b:"offer ritual sacrifice ",c:"hunt for antelopes  ",d:"have a  new baby."},section:"Question is  based on Oyono’s Old man hand the medal",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:105,question:"The medal in Oyono’s The Old man and the  two sons and his: ",option:{a:"house ",b:"horse  ",c:"land ",d:"Job"},section:"Question is  based on Oyono’s Old man hand the medal",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:106,question:"Kelara in Oyono’s The Old man and the Medal is: ",option:{a:"Mvodo’s sister ",b:"commandant’s maid  ",c:"Meka’s wife ",d:"Agatha’s cousin."},section:"Question is  based on Oyono’s Old man hand the medal",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:107,question:"In Oyonon’s The Old Man and the Medal, Ignatius Obebe isa : ",option:{a:"driver ",b:"soldier ",c:"carpenter ",d:"catechist."},section:"Question is  based on Oyono’s Old man hand the medal",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:108,question:"The medal in Oyono’s The Old man and the medal is a symbol of: ",option:{a:"colonial deceit ",b:"African pride  ",c:"genuine reward for loyalty ",d:"respect and honour"},section:"Question is  based on Oyono’s Old man hand the medal",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:109,question:"Dancing through blooming thorns” in Gbemisola  Adeoti’s Naked soles” connotes: ",option:{a:"hoeing a field of thorns ",b:"dancing  in a keen competition ",c:"being merry amidst suffering",d:"playing flowers and plants."},section:"Question is are based on selected African poems.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:110,question:"In Gbemisola Adeoti’s Naked Soles”, the expression red milk of grief’ refers to: ",option:{a:"wine  ",b:"Ink ",c:"blood ",d:"palm-oil"},section:"Question is are based on selected African poems.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:111,question:"In Masizi Kunene’s “A Heritage of Liberation; this season’ refers to the period of: ",option:{a:"oppression ",b:"freedom  ",c:"migration  ",d:"resettlement"},section:"Question is are based on selected African poems.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:112,question:"“Eagle in Kunene’s  “A Heritage  of  Liberation” is a symbol of: ",option:{a:"deceit ",b:"peace ",c:"agility ",d:"death."},section:"Question is are based on selected African poems.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:113,question:"The tone in Gbemisola Adeoti’s Naked soles” is that of ",option:{a:"reconciliation  ",b:"lamentation  ",c:"exhortation ",d:"admiration"},section:"Question is are based on selected African poems.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:114,question:"The attitude of the poet-Persona toward bats in D.H. Lawrence’s “Bats” is that of ",option:{a:"revulsion ",b:"veneration  ",c:"admiration  ",d:"indifference."},section:"Questions is based on Non-African Poetry",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:115,question:"In China, according to D.H. Lawrence, bats are symbols of: ",option:{a:"death  ",b:"birth ",c:"caution ",d:"joy"},section:"Questions is based on Non-African Poetry",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:116,question:"In Wendy Cope’s Sonnet VII,  poetry is regarded as a God –given weapon to: ",option:{a:"musicians ",b:"recluses ",c:"nomads ",d:"pilgrims."},section:"Questions is based on Non-African Poetry",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:117,question:"The greatest challenge to the poet-persona in Andrew Marvell’s “To His Coy Mistress’ is : ",option:{a:"chariot ",b:"love  ",c:"time ",d:"youth"},section:"Questions is based on Non-African Poetry",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:118,question:"But the pigs were so clever that they could think of a way around every difficulty. As for the horses, they know every inch of the field and in fact understood the business of mowing and raking”. The dominant literary device in the excerpt above is ",option:{a:"repetition ",b:"mimesis ",c:"ellipsis ",d:"personification."},section:"Question is  based on literary appreciation",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:119,question:"“The dairy maids and men had flocked down from their cottages and out of the dairy-house with the arrival of the cows from the meads: the maids walking in  patterns, not on account of weather, but to keep their shoes above the mulch of the barton”. The setting of the above  passage can be described as: ",option:{a:"urban  ",b:"celestial ",c:"pastoral  ",d:"religious."},section:"Question is  based on literary appreciation",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:120,question:"“O mother, my mother!...How could I be expected to know? I was a child when I left this house four months ago. Why didn’t  you tell me there was danger in men-folk? Why didn’t you warn me?” the speech above achieves its literary effect through the use of: ",option:{a:"litotes  ",b:"onomatopoeia ",c:"allusion  ",d:"repetition."},section:"Question is  based on literary appreciation",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:121,question:"“The animals saw no reason to disbelieve him, especially as they could no longer remember very clearly  what conditions had been like before the rebellion. All the same, there were days when they felt that they would sooner have had less figures and more food”. The tone of the passage above is quite: ",option:{a:"exhilarating ",b:"cynical ",c:"optimistic ",d:"obsequious."},section:"Question is  based on literary appreciation",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:122,question:"“We are tired of waiting for another war our trees their leaves have shed the winter has come and gone spring flowers have blossomed and withered” in line 2 of the poem above, the poet uses:",option:{a:"ellipsis ",b:"alliteration ",c:"inversion  ",d:"oxymoron."},section:"Question is  based on literary appreciation",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:123,question:"The poet personal in the poem above is: ",option:{a:"resigned to fate  ",b:"a holy man  ",c:"a daily traveler  ",d:"suffering but optimistic. "},section:`“I come and go
a pilgrim
grubbily unkempt
stubbornly cheerful
defiantly whistling hope
and grubbing for crumbs of success
out of all near-defeats.
`,image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:224,question:"‘I simply don’t understand what the matter with everybody is today. Everybody let me down, and ...’ The speaker above is referring to",option:{a:"Fosuwa and Maidservant",b:"Hannah and George",c:"Aaron and Maanan",d:"Lawyer B and Mrs B"},section:"Based on J.C. De Graft’s  	Sons and Daughter. ",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:225,question:"Maanan expresses dislike for Lawyer B because of",option:{a:"his condemnation of  her choice career",b:"his recent advances towards her",c:"the betrayal of her father’s trust",d:"the betrayal of his wife’s trust"},section:"Based on J.C. De Graft’s  	Sons and Daughter. ",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:226,question:"The traditional order in the play is represented by",option:{a:"Mrs. B",b:"Hannah",c:"Maanan",d:"Aunt"},section:"Based on J.C. De Graft’s  	Sons and Daughter. ",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:227,question:"Where does the play take place?",option:{a:"On the street",b:"In George’s place",c:"In Aunt’s house",d:"In Ofosu’s place"},section:"Based on J.C. De Graft’s  	Sons and Daughter. ",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:228,question:"‘O’ deadly sin! O rude unthankfulness! Thy fault our law calls death, but the kind Prince, Taking thy 		part, hath rushed aside the law and turned that black word.....’ Deadly sin refers to the",option:{a:"suicide of Juliet",b:"suicide of  Romeo",c:"murder of  Paris",d:"murder of  Tybalt"},section:"Based on William Shakespeare’s  	Romeo and Juliet.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:229,question:"The play is mostly written in",option:{a:"blank verse",b:"free verse",c:"metres",d:"foot"},section:"Based on William Shakespeare’s  	Romeo and Juliet.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:230,question:"‘O” serpent heart, hid with a flowering face!’ The statement refers to",option:{a:"Juliet",b:"Romeo",c:"Tybalt",d:"Benvolio"},section:"Based on William Shakespeare’s  	Romeo and Juliet.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:231,question:"The spatial setting of the play is",option:{a:"Athens",b:"Verona",c:"Padua",d:"Venice"},section:"Based on William Shakespeare’s  	Romeo and Juliet.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:232,question:"Romeo is banished to Mantua because he",option:{a:"kills Tybalt in a street duel",b:"marries Juliet without parental consent",c:"attends Capulet’s party uninvited",d:"attempts to kill Paris his rival"},section:"Based on William Shakespeare’s  	Romeo and Juliet.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:233,question:"In the novel, the society puts high value on",option:{a:"egalitarianism",b:"male ascendancy",c:"procreation",d:"gender equity"},section:"Based on Buchi Emecheta’s  	The Joys of  Motherhood.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:234,question:"The medicine man links the lump discovered on the head of Nnu Ego at birth, to the",option:{a:"possession of physical admirable qualities that makes her an epitome of perfection",b:"wound inflicted on the slave woman buried with Agbadi’s wife",c:"coming back of the Agunwa to the society to live again",d:"ill-luck and tragic events attributed to a predestined fate."},section:"Based on Buchi Emecheta’s  	The Joys of  Motherhood.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:235,question:"The constant companions of  Nnaife family are",option:{a:"togetherness and happiness",b:"poverty and hunger",c:"sickness and joblessness",d:"disagreement and humiliation"},section:"Based on Buchi Emecheta’s  	The Joys of  Motherhood.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:236,question:"The disagreement between Mvondo and Nticentres on the latter’s claim to have",option:{a:"Assisted Meka in getting the medal",b:"eaten the entire entrails of a sheep",c:"eaten more than his share of the food",d:"been in a Whiteman’s office"},section:"Based on Ferdina  and Oyono’s  	The Old Man and the Medal.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:237,question:"In the novel, the colonialists treat the Africans with",option:{a:"kids gloves",b:"disdain",c:"indifference",d:"honour"},section:"Based on Ferdina  and Oyono’s  	The Old Man and the Medal.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:238,question:"The Ministry of Peace is concerned with making",option:{a:"instruments",b:"weapons",c:"wars",d:"reconciliation"},section:"Based on George Orwell’s  	Nineteen Eighty-Four.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:239,question:"The subject matter of the novel is",option:{a:"Totalitarian dictatorship",b:"exploitation and cruelty",c:"retributive justice",d:"class segregation"},section:"Based on George Orwell’s  	Nineteen Eighty-Four.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:240,question:"How did Winston start his rebellion against the state?",option:{a:"By engaging in anti-party activities",b:"By keeping a private diary",c:"When he started a secret affair",d:"When he spied on the party"},section:"Based on George Orwell’s  	Nineteen Eighty-Four.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:241,question:"The party seeks power for",option:{a:"the nation",b:"its own sake",c:"its members",d:"peoples’ sake"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:242,question:"A play which mainly aims at provoking excessive laughter is 	called",option:{a:"a tragi-comedy",b:"comedy",c:"a farce",d:"satire"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:243,question:"Both comedy and tragedy have",option:{a:"happy ending",b:"climax",c:"tragic hero",d:"stanza"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:244,question:"A formal dignified speech or writing praising a person or a thing for past or present deeds is",option:{a:"premiere",b:"eulogy",c:"anthology",d:"lampoon"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:245,question:"The narrative style in which the hero tells his own story directly is the",option:{a:"objective",b:"subjective",c:"first-person",d:"third-person"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:246,question:"The physical, historical or cultural background of a literary work is referred to as",option:{a:"episode",b:"plot",c:"time",d:"setting"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:247,question:"A plot structure that defies chronology can be described as",option:{a:"open-ended",b:"circular",c:"episodic",d:"organic"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:248,question:"Pun as a literary device deals with",option:{a:"placing two opposite phrase",b:"placing words side by side",c:"playing on words",d:"arrangement of words"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:249,question:"In a narrative poem, the poet attempts to",option:{a:"summarize a story",b:"describe a place",c:"preach a sermon",d:"tell a story"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:250,question:"The account of experiences of an individual during the course 	of a journey is known as",option:{a:"a travelogue",b:"an autobiography",c:"a catalogue",d:"a memoir"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:251,question:"Satirical writing employs",option:{a:"epigram",b:"synecdoche",c:"irony",d:"onomatopoeia"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:252,question:"The person being addressed above is a",option:{a:"soldier",b:"student",c:"domestic servant",d:"lawyer"},section:"‘Basha: You dumb skull of a bone head.... you will face court martial for this. You look everywhere? You search inside toilet bowl? ( Wole Soyinka: King Baabu)",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:253,question:"From the tone of the speech above, the speaker is obviously",option:{a:"enraged",b:"lackadaisical",c:"elated",d:"happy"},section:"‘Basha: You dumb skull of a bone head.... you will face court martial for this. You look everywhere? You search inside toilet bowl? ( Wole Soyinka: King Baabu)",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:254,question:"The mood conveyed in the excerpt above is one of",option:{a:"sadness",b:"frustration",c:"sympathy",d:"dilemma"},section:"‘That year the harvest was sad, like a funeral, and many farmers wept as they dug up the miserable yams. One man tied his cloth to a tree branch and hanged himself.’ (Chinua Achebe: Things Fall Apart)",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:255,question:"The rhyme scheme in the excerpt above is",option:{a:"bbaa",b:"aabb",c:"abab",d:"abba"},section:"That age is best which is the first,<br> 	When youth and blood are warmer, <br> 	But being spent, the worse, and worst <br> 	Time still succeed the former. ",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:256,question:"The subject matter of the extract above is",option:{a:"Storm",b:"sea waves",c:"house movement",d:"earthquake"},section:"But the towering earth was tired sitting in one position. She moved, suddenly, and the houses crumbled, the mountains heaved horribly, and the work of a million years was lost	",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:257,question:"From the poem above, shadow means",option:{a:"famine",b:"bleak future",c:"period of sufferings",d:"abstract ideas"},section:"And your laughter like a flame<br>	 	Piercing the shadows<br> 	Has revealed Africa to me beyond<br> 	The snow of yesterday<br>",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:258,question:"The speaker in the excerpt above is",option:{a:"hopeless",b:"uncertain",c:"afraid",d:"confident"},section:"Don’t panic. Be calm. If you are somehow upset.... try to regain your exposure.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:259,question:"The poem can be described as",option:{a:"a lyric",b:"an epic",c:"a sonnet",d:"an elegy"},section:"Move him into the sun,<br> 	Gently its touch awoke him once, ,<br> 	At home, whispering of  fields unsown,<br> 	Always it woke him even in France,<br> 	Until this morning and this snow,<br> 	If anything might rouse him now ,<br> 	This kind old sun will know,<br> 	Think how it wakes the seeds,<br> 	Woke, once, the clays of a cold star,<br> 	Are limbs, so dear achieved, are,<br> 	sides Full nerved still warm too hard ,<br> 	to stir Was it, for this the clay grew,<br> 	tall? O what made fatuous sunbeams ,<br> 	toil To break earth’s sleep at all. ,<br>",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:260,question:"The theme of the poem is",option:{a:"futility of  life",b:"distortion of  life",c:"creation of  life",d:"vanity of  life"},section:"Move him into the sun,<br> 	Gently its touch awoke him once, ,<br> 	At home, whispering of  fields unsown,<br> 	Always it woke him even in France,<br> 	Until this morning and this snow,<br> 	If anything might rouse him now ,<br> 	This kind old sun will know,<br> 	Think how it wakes the seeds,<br> 	Woke, once, the clays of a cold star,<br> 	Are limbs, so dear achieved, are,<br> 	sides Full nerved still warm too hard ,<br> 	to stir Was it, for this the clay grew,<br> 	tall? O what made fatuous sunbeams ,<br> 	toil To break earth’s sleep at all. ,<br>",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:261,question:"The rhyme scheme of the stanza above is",option:{a:"aabb",b:"abab",c:"bbaa",d:"abba"},section:"A cursing rogue with a merry farce,<br>  	A bundle of rags upon a crutch, ,<br> 	Stumbled upon that windy place,<br> 	Called cruachan, and it was as much.	",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"}],i={subject:e,status:200,total:62,data:a};export{a as data,i as default,t as status,e as subject,o as total};
